Okay, we'll call the order of the regular meeting for the moderate city council for July 19, 2021
Public in put around schedule personal appearances
We have a deal
All right three considered gender staff recommends we approve items four through six. I'll make a motion. We approve
Second
Hi
All right
7 where you're going to table. Great
8 budget amendment number 22 does 0 1
Fund grant police correcting errors from inputting budget from this deal. Let's give it to get up here
Since then
So during the budget season the very end of the last year to the last two weeks we had several
Can you donate the credit down during the last two weeks before the budget was approved we had a lot of staff changes
I wasn't even in my office not trying to make excuses, but just frankly
We didn't do the job of approving the budget at the end you have something sitting at your table
That is the budget summary that you approved the two places highlighted
Indicate two errors that we made
One of them is a process error and we've corrected the process, but in that two weeks
When someone loses a person they bring it what we call a pink sheet because it's literally pink and we
Finance is one of the people that signs saying yes, you have this money to rehire this person
Lots of people sign this sheet
That was somebody that was a maintenance three they had several positions open
So when they hired somebody we got a green sheet it didn't say which person it was replacing so we that money got inadvertently
Lower to that new person who came in is like a maintenance one
So we're asking that they could have their money back to pay their maintenance three the other two
Literally was a linking error
We had four grants and for the police fund
So two
Spread sheets a link to each other and they're looking at one certain cell. Well if you put in a line, which is exactly what happened all that information goes down
But it's still looking at the one cell. So that is what happened the rest
revenues are correct, but we haven't given the ability to to spend those revenues.
So it's for grants and for the police fund, and part of that police fund is like that
Jack Fletcher.
There are no, I think there's a big budgeted to spend, but we just want to give them the
ability that they did.
So I'm asking you to approve this amendment for those three years.
But you guys all aware what the Jack Fletcher is running is, going?
Can you explain that real quick just so or about that?
Oh, I know that the library and the police and the fire all got donation money.
I think the man passed, and they got a significant amount.
Was it 144 for police and fire in like 74 for library?
Is that sound about right?
Something about that.
That's a significant money.
So we had about that to the certain entities, I think the county got some, and they're
a bit to different levels of the money that they're talking about for the police department.
So what are the differences we're approving?
It's surely not 19 and one-nine-two.
No, no, no, no, those are where the numbers should have been, so the amendment was in the packet.
The total amount is 2.2 million, 519,900, 4,043 cents, because grants were significant.
Grants were 2.3 million.
The parks money that we inadvertently reduce 17,000, 435 or 72, and then the police fund was $158,036.
So the total was 2.5 million, and that is in the packet, the amendment.
And some of the grants aren't grants that we've actually received.
Sometimes we budget the revenue and the expenditure, but if we don't get the revenue, they don't
spend it.
You know, a page I was on?
Oh, no.
No.
I'm not.
Everyone.
If you would pay the bills, I don't know, man.
It just gets grown at $27,000, and we sell it, so I can get to it.
I wouldn't quite, there you go.
I didn't word my question very well, I think I was just asking, what is this the actual
difference?
Two and a half million dollars.
Yes.
It's not, it's not that we have an additional two and a half million dollars, because they
were presented in the budget accurately as revenues and expenditures, if I'm understanding
correctly.
The revenues were accurately presented for the grants and the police fund, but the expenditures
were...
amount by that amount 2.5. So the money was already budgeted. The revenue was budgeted but not the
expenditure. Okay, so what was the end result? The bottom at the end. The bottom right
end corner of that spreadsheet. Well, I'd have to understand you got to make it go out. Yeah. But
it's surely having impact at the end. Only the only the revenue was already is on that spreadsheet.
The revenue is at the top. I understand. But the expenditure is not at the bottom. Let me
make sense. Okay, I'll work on my questions. I don't, I'm not there. So if you look at the
special revenue column, you'll see at the top where it says total estimated resources is 10 million.
Yes, my four. And at the bottom where it says total estimated expenditures, it says 1.9 million.
That needs to say about 2 million more than that. Just to make things balanced. Right. Yes.
Just so they can spin the money. If they get the grid, it's been the money. No, okay.
Yep. With you now. Thank you. It does. Maybe the other question is a little bit out for me, but
I'll make a motion. Oh, second.
Done, Cole? Hi. Davis? Hi. Summer? Hi. Parker? Hi.
Nine. Approve ATSI contract and authorized city manager signature, Mr. DiVannell.
This four is for a software, but we can do our employee key of that. We can do health and professional
management. There's just several things. I don't know if you guys are familiar with our pay.
How we do our pay with the men. Right. But all from the city employees, there's 30% or 70% that's not taken in.
There are salary increases are based on their evaluations. And now we have done evaluations in the past
is in your manual. We have a PDF document that we print out. We fill it out.
We pass it all around the building for the appropriate signatures and we have to scan it inside of them and it's just a long process
And what this is this is for software so we can do this electronically and so while I'm asking for it to not as just to approve
The software and both signature so we can join the train first century. What's the software cost?
$10,000. That already in the budget. It's already been budgeted. Yes
Well, I know our city manager's not to you guys
So I'm sure he's all all for this, but yeah, I'm sure it's gonna be easier because we're outworked that's why we do it
It's all electronic
You don't have to pass it on the papers and get all the signatures. It's makes it flow a lot of these here
You know the questions for Cindy in that. I'll make a motion we approve
Second
Parker. Bye. Uncle. Hi. Sunburn. Thanks. All right. Thanks, Cindy.
There are 10 presentation from my area economic development services and the regional chamber by Charlotte. How?
Including the vegetable chambers staff that I can
Go back from Texas today, so for me
We want to just update you guys on kind of where we've been working on and where we're at and days
A reminder this is our focus for 2021. It's business retention and expansion. The workforce on
New Yorkshire and recruitment
We also want to remind you that the city of Miami is a great partner with us and these are what their friends are used for
It's for accounting
for advertising for subscriptions and dues insurance and repairs and maintenance on the building houses the chamber hand in my
Ontario economic development service. I want to go over business retention and expansion with you because this has been our biggest effort this year
It's also the states focus
So some of the things we've worked on in the last three months since I updated you is we have formed a committee on business
retention and expansion. We have a list of about 20 manufacturers or primary employers in the county. We've visited about half
But we hope to have them finish up at the end of August
The goal of this is we go in and ask the questions like who's your biggest supplier who's your biggest vendor
What's your biggest challenge? What can you have at night? Are you looking to grow?
We take all that information and we'll put it in a report like the Green Country manufacturing allow Alliance used to do and that work
would be available to community members to use city leaders and also to our
manufacturers so they can see what's going on as well. It also helps us target
recruitment. So for instance we have a lot of plastic manufacturers and you know
we know that if we recruited a plastic resident maker here it would save them a
lot of money so we know that that needs to be a target that these kind of questions
can flush that out for us. So we have a group of community leaders that are
part of that committee and they go around and ask these questions in a
conversation with our manufacturers. We'll compile that and hopefully have a
report for you in the fall. Our goal is to do this every six months. We are
going to do things a little differently in the most communities. Most communities
just do this with primary employers, mostly manufacturers. We do think we want to
focus on retail and so we would like to do a retail BRD starting in January where the
committee will go out and do kind of the same thing with a little bit of twist because you
don't have to retell or swipe the same questions. And we've also done the
team manufacturing visits. We show an exchange rate of over 80% of our
existing manufacturers with a job count close to 15 new jobs. So we're a little
over 50% through the BRD process and out of those that we've visited so far 80% of them
have expansion plans in the works in the very near future. These aren't five or 10 years
out. These are 12 and 18 months out. That isn't great thing for us to know as well
because we can work closely with them for capital investment and Tyler has been
helping us with infrastructure needs that come up as they look to expand and also look
for funding for those infrastructure needs or for the expansion. There are some incentives
out there that are kind of unique because of COVID. So are we making sure our companies get
whatever they need to continue to grow? We show a job count just from the expansion of
just the 90% of over 50 jobs and remember those are primary jobs versus not primary jobs.
So main job is to recruit primary jobs which means they make it up money to support their
family. That's why our focus is so often on manufacturing. Since March, May is assisted
nine companies with direct services including workforce financing options and partnerships. We've
also in coordination with the Migra Regional Chamber of Commerce hosted the Secretary of Agriculture
at the Rivencoding last week for his processing. We were part of the getting a 200,000-dollar
grant which they used along with some of their capital resources to add square footage.
It cut their time and half, but they are still looked out to June 2022. So you need me processed,
you very don't list, and all of our main processors are in this. So we'll continue to look for
resources for them. Strategic workforce and we have, in the spring, hosted job fairs in Miami,
Grove, Langley, and the NVIDIA and we won't be doing those anytime soon unless we're specifically
asked because they're just not working right now. Workforce is in a very unique situation.
As I'm sure you all know, finding workers has become extremely difficult.
Oklahoma right now is ranked eight in the country and unemployment rate.
which means we are at 3.7% and but four collectively we were at 3.2. So, you know, it's to the point now
we're partnering with the city and we're looking at quality of life and have to look at group people
to into the area or drive it to the area to build our jobs. And Mates was honored to host the Greater
Grand Lake Region Hero Area of Education Summit and we got the High School Center Michael Archron
in Oklahoma Minor and Autismation. While the summit was focused on a pathway for aerospace jobs
that did open a conversation into other ways to partner and pathways that the high schools
that bridge and higher education institutions can use that we've seen work across the state.
We're going to continue those conversations hopefully a little more specific. We've already talked a little
bit about these in teacher two or some partnerships with NEO and some of our manufacturers.
And we're going to keep those conversations moving forward. We'll be hosting our educational
partners to discuss long-term workforce goals for the region within the next 30 to 60 days. The goal
of that will be to really kickstart what was above. Senator Bertrand has been working hard at the state level
about apprenticeships. They're extremely difficult for manufacturers and primary employers to register for.
So none of them want to do it but we know they work. So what can we do to help make that process easier
than our goal is to win the pilot program in the mighty region. So we're in the middle of
those conversations now. Entrepreneurship, we've worked with 10 manufacturers in the last three months
so we're down a little bit because in January, if you're great march, we've worked with that 20.
It's a total for over 30 that we assisted this year. We're looking at location, financing
options, business plan strategies, and more. And we are also helping Dr. Stafford with the SBBC office
that he is helping to recruit to any of them. We will work in partnership with them. That will be a huge
help. We did have our first entrepreneurship committee meeting. It was small so we wanted to grow that.
So if you know an entrepreneur that you think would be a great mentor, let me know. I did talk to
E-Latian with and he has been a step in and do some help with us. The goal is to do some things like
local shark tanks, mentorship programs so that our entrepreneurs have what they need to succeed. They're
very creative. A lot of times they ignore the business side and that's to their bedroom. So we want to
make sure that we're filling all those gaps for that innovation. And then we also picked up two new
memberships this year as you all know for the space that we will begin marketing on that shared space.
We've been talking with O-Doc with the Department of Commerce and they're going to work with Mades and a
couple of shared spaces in the state to just kind of promote that concept. So instead of an incubator
where you have to have someone on hand at all times, a shared space is a little more informal,
or people can buy an membership or rent an office at a discounted rate. And then I'm there if they have
to be helped or if I can connect them with someone who helped their business to grow.
Lastly, recruitment, as you all know, in April, we announced communication solutions that was coming to my Emma.
This is an inbound call center, so they do inbound and retention calls.
They are at 100, I believe 120 employees right now.
Their goal is at least 200, but we have indications that there is future road, we just can't talk about it all the time.
But we have assisted them with the use of our facilities.
So the first three weeks, they were at the chambers so that they could begin hiring right away.
And they were doing training as well at our facility.
We've assisted them with facility needs. Thank you, plus.
We've also assisted them with meetings with NEO and they're working on a partnership where they would become a large employer of any of students.
So we're helping that partnership with Pelevin, so that we can provide transportation for their employees as well as partnership with Cherokee Nation's workforce grant program.
Which will help subsidize and offset some of their sort of costs as they continue to train people.
Their campaign classes are every two weeks.
Their goal is 40 to 50 people and they're getting about 30 to 40.
Which is still really good, but it's part of it's time to imagine them because they want to grow super fast.
Um, we also attended the Zalph-Zalph Dallas culture. This was the first time in the Department of Commerce and Select of Oklahoma did a call trip.
Um, select a Oklahoma course is the group of economic developers in this state that worked together to promote the state within Oklahoma Department of Commerce.
Generally, in January, we have a big reception down there.
We invite scientists all those from all over Texas because that's where a lot of our relationships are.
And we talk about how great Oklahoma is and we try to work some deals.
Because of COVID, we did a call trip this year, later in the year instead of doing anything.
So, I attended seven meetings. All of them were with site consultants and not companies.
So, it's kind of a good thing because then they go out and work with a lot of companies and you're not just meeting with one.
We did retail manufacturing and incremental services and we're hoping to follow up with some of those meetings.
They were very interested in the fact that we had landed at 150 jobs.
So the retail people are kind of anxious to get here.
Um, so those were good meetings. We also hosted one site visit with a company from how to stay in partnership with the city of Miami.
And we just found out last week that this project is on hold.
So, Tyler and I are pretty frustrated right now because it went really well.
And we were told that it was going to go through.
Um, the company did purchase an Miami manufacturer.
They are here. We do expect things to raise their wages. They got indicated that will happen.
We do expect future growth for them. But they had a little bit of work force issues on their own.
And so, um, the project is on standby.
And then lastly, we're going to continue to market sites in Miami including our set building for manufacturing development in our region.
So, we're going to start looking outside the box and try to figure out some different ways to get out there.
I will tell you on the recruitment side we have not been answering.
Oh, I've been answering.
a lot of the RFPs from the state. And the reason why is because our manufacturers are really
frustrated right now with workforce and I feel like there are about this. 70% of your growth
comes from what you have. And so while we are still looking for good projects for Miami, we're
super focused right now on the companies we have here and how we can help them because they are
and all trying to grow really fast about who we consider those companies we had talked to you
have had their best year ever. And they want to grow here. So we need to help them make that happen.
Winning at 500 employee projects is not the way to do that. So that's been our focus as business
retention and expansion. As you guys know, the chamber was sending Morris has really started their
programming this year. We just had the Gallo. We felt like it was a huge success. We absolutely had
great time and of course, he felt like what was our impact award winner. And so we were honored to be able to
do that for our cities has to probably over 15 ribbon cuttings. This is the beginning of the year.
We're also putting back in women in business as well as our legislative agenda. So be sharing people
look out for those things so that if you want participate or get involved. I have statement. Yes.
The presentation a year ago was distinctly different and far less positive. No one will brag on it.
Thank you very much. We've been working. I feel like fast and hot hard.
But it's been a long and if it wasn't for Tyler and Bo and Bliss. I mean, the people on our committees,
there's no way we could have done this. Tyler and I are really good team. I'm just going to tell you all
like we play off each other really well these meetings. So I hope we get to do that more on it. There are
projects that we're working on that we can't talk about. What they're going to tell you is I've never
ever one time had to question Tyler's own reality and the fact that he had an eye for about
two months or the only people that knew the name of a company. Both of them we didn't really good.
There are other good things in the work that we can't talk about there right now. So thank you very much.
Yes. I also have statement. Last year about this time, he stood here and I was pretty hard on it.
And I told you, but I'm all about getting credit were credits to do and you've really been doing
a great job for us. And I've seen it firsthand and I've seen it with my own eyes.
I think the team, like you said, that's working with you with Bo, being involved in Tyler,
Bethel Cook, being a mentor for you, has really really helped things out. So again, I give credit
for credits to do. Good job. Keep it up. I see good things in our future.
I think we're headed in there right now. I think we're going to talk about that. We really have some good things.
Can you know, the communication policy that she mentioned, the call center?
You know, we landed that right in the middle of COVID.
And that's a stimulus thing that's came out right when they started firing.
And that's not something that many towns our size did was land a new business during
COVID.
So it's still a top probably top 20 project for the state right now as far as job counts.
And if we don't watch out, they may be our largest employer in this community.
So it's really good to be able to do that with what we've been going on last year and
yeah, for so, and the people that are working there in the communication industry seem to really
love working there.
I've seen their stuff on Facebook and the posts that they make encourage other people
to work there are really enjoying where they work.
So I like the fact that it gives us some diversification to.
So when I was in Dallas, it wasn't just for manufacturing and I could say, well, we just landed
a call center with 150 seats and they're like, really, you can do that there.
That opens a conversation for us to recruit other back office jobs, which is,
this is the first occasion for our workforce.
So I think it was a good one.
The other thing I like about the call center is it's inbound.
It's inbound.
It's less pressure on our local folks because they're not co-calling people and being high pressure
sales such that they're just being a lot now.
They're doing brilliant.
The training is actually really good and we've just had a meeting last week that we'd encourage
that to this guy just like even the communication classes that they can tailor towards
communication solutions so that the people that come out of those classes would have a job.
Thank you.
Any other questions for?
Nope.
I'm just, thank you, Charlotte.
For all you do.
Thank you for the amazing job and we know it.
We appreciate it.
All right.
Number 11, other new business, the main reason since posting in this agenda.
12 staff reports, 13 mayor and council, community, and council.
I'm not gonna get anything.
I got one that I got one there.
I always pay my electric bill, my city electric bill, all line through the payment, all
my payment bill.
And of course, that's changed here recently.
And so this was my first time to pay it through the new online bill pay.
It was so much easier.
I love it.
It was a great change.
It was, I could do it one payment instead of two, like I had to always before, and the fee was lower.
So, but it told you more about your bill, it was just a lot smoother transition from me
anyway to pay my bill that way.
So, great job council for about that end.
Yeah.
That's all I got.
So, you know, by all the time, they only got a 14, so you manage communications.
So, we're gonna...
start putting my communications before your communications.
So you don't announce anything that I would announce.
But no, the mayor's right.
Our new online payment process with Paymentis has gone live.
That's never a small feat to put something in that integrates
with your financial system.
But it's in. It's working.
It does offer a lot more, not only is it lower.
The fee per transaction with a higher threshold.
But again, customers can pay their bills through PayPal, Amazon Pay, Venmo,
and Walmart Pay, as well as debit.
So it gives us a lot more opportunities there.
Again, it doesn't agree with our income system.
And anyway, we're extremely excited about having that in.
And can't wait to really now get out and publicize and drive utilization.
And so hopefully in the future what I want to do is start bringing new utilization numbers.
How many people are using that today?
And prior to the new system.
We'll get the word out.
We'll start, you know, really encouraging people to use it.
And then bring you some utilization numbers of how many more citizens are using that.
Which will be fantastic.
The other thing that I wanted to announce is I'm extremely excited to announce today
and to the council that we have filled our HR director position, which was vacated recently by Kim Horn,
and Cindy Vanover, who applied for the position.
She has 14 years with the city.
But we did an exhaustive search.
They're locally and had 14 or I should say regionally had at least 12 highly qualified HR folks apply for this position.
We went through an exhaustive interview process.
And I'm very proud to say that our Cindy was the cream of the crop.
And definitely.
Once you spoke earlier, almost congratulated her and I thought I'd better wait.
She just, we couldn't be happier with the way the process turned out.
She just, by the entire team, was voted unanimously as our top choice.
And it was for good reason her experience showed through in the interview process her knowledge of processes.
And the exciting thing she brought in to just new ideas, things that she wants to look at and try and work to further evolve the city.
And that was really exciting because not only does she have things she wants to do, but she has a good idea of how it will fit and what.
I mean, not fit.
But anyway, she just absolutely fit with our near term objectives and we're excited to have her on board and thrilled to announce it today.
Let's great news this.
we did that kind of search and had that kind of applicants and one of our own was the top
pick. So, absolutely, we done it all the way up.
Number 15, this meeting will now be continued from council chambers and reconvening the staff rooms from purpose.
I wouldn't be home yet anyway, I'd still be working, so no matter me.
I told my wife, I think I got way on these.
We're all right.
Talk about slow.
And you're called me old.
That's pretty sad.
That's a deal.
We're all in there still.
Okay.
So, we're back in regular session at nine.
And back in regular session.
So, after the executive session, we have a couple of motions to make.
We need a motion to authorize the letter from the city attorney and the city manager and city council
to be sent to underground reserve.
So, no.
Second.
Davis.
Dougal.
Hi.
The thing we need to authorize is a given the city attorney, the authority to initiate civil
action against Robert W. Lehi at 15E Southwest, for living in the condemn structure with
no utilities.
So, Robert Lehi.
Robert Lehi at all.
Yes.
So, move.
Say.
Did you say?
Okay.
Dougal.
Hi.
Parker.
Davis.
Hi.
Good evening.
Good evening guys.
Okay.
так.'s.
Cheers.
Justin.
Okay.
Junior treats.
Eighter Class.
Second.